♫ I tuo i macil a staldaron
(The strength, the weapon, the needs of the valiant)
♫ Marinyë Cor[ma]
(Let the Ring be your weapon)
♫ I tuo i macil
(The strength, the weapon)
♫ A lelyat túrenna
(Go to victory)
...burzum-ishi krimpatul...
(...in the darkness bind them...)
Ash nazg durbatulûk
(One ring to rule them all)
Ash nazg gimbatul
(One ring to find them)
...Daghburz-ishi makha gulshu darulu...
...In the Land of Mordor where the Shadows lie...)
Westu Aragorn hál.
(Be-thou Aragorn well.)
Ash nazg thrakatum
(Bring the One Ring)
♫ Naegriel moë
(Softly pining)
♫ [A ch]uil anann me perónen
(For a life long lived, for a love half given)
♫ Síliel mae
(Softly shining)
♫ I ngîl firiel
(I saw a star fade)
♫ Dúr i fuin
(The dark was too deep)
♫ An i naun ului
(For what never was)
♫ An chuil anann cuinannen
(For a life long lived)
Ada.
(Dad.)
♫ An i naun ului
(For what never was)
♫ Am meleth perónen
(For a love half given)
Ada...
(Dad...)
♫ Ehtelë lína, manna lelyal[ye]?
(The fountain is still, where did you go?)
♫ Ored, gwanwen ost in giliath
(No warning, the citadel of the stars is gone)
♫ Dannen Osgiliath
(Osgiliath has fallen)
♫ Sílant calad Dûn
(A light shone in the west)
♫ Tollen Rochon 'Lân
(The White Rider had come)
♫ Mennen nored dîn
(Their race was over)
♫ Go vegil tolo hí 'ni men 'war
(Come armed, no other end to this road)
♫ Elo! Andúril
(Behold! Andúril)
Ónen i-Estel Edain.
(I gave hope to men.)
Ú-chebin Estel anim.
(I have kept no hope for myself.)
♫ Hollen i ven
(The way is shut)
♫ In gyrth han agorer
(It was made by those who are dead)
♫ A han beriar in gyrth
(And the Dead keep it)
♫ Hollen i ven
(The way is shut)
Katmuda! / Gorosh!
(Death to Men! / Louder!)
♫ Hollen i ven
(The way is shut)
Gurut!
(Death!)
♫ Ristais dúath
(Shreds of shadow)
♫ Tellin i Neder
(The Nine have come)
♫ Gurth renia
(Death has taken wing)
♫ Meditha han phan
(He will eat it all)
♫ Meditha ardhon
(Eat all the world)
♫ Nerchennin o chuil
(Torn from life)
♫ Coll am na waewath goeyl
(Borne aloft by fell winds)
♫ Tellin i Neder
(The Nine have come)
♫ Gurth renia
(Death has taken wing)
Aiya Eärendil Elenion Ancalima!
(Hail Eärendil brightest of the stars!)
♫ [Coll] am na waewath goeyl
(Borne aloft by fell winds)
♫ Tellin i Neder
(The Nine have come)
♫ Gurth renia
(Death has taken wing)
♫ Meditha han phan
(He will eat it all)
♫ Meditha ardhon
(Eat all the world)
♫ Úrianner i eryd
(The mountains burned)
♫ Sui ros garan dannant
(As red dew fell)
♫ Or pheli Pelennor
(On the fields of Pelennor)
♫ Dollost - dîr cuiol 'ar nin degi!
(You fool - no living man can kill me!)
♫ Le echelithar aen Athar fuin ban
(You will be borne away Beyond all darkness)
♫ Rhaw lîn mannen
(Your flesh devoured)
♫ Ind tham lîn
(Your shriveled mind)
♫ Lanc na chen be-thobas
(Left naked to the lidless eye)
♫ Ofer endun
(Over death)
♫ Of lyre, of lífe
(Out of loss, out of life)
♫ tó langum wuldre
(unto long glory)
♫ Hé.
He.
♫ Immen dúath caeda
(Shadow lies between us)
♫ Sui tollech, tami gwanna[thach] omen
(As you came, so you shall leave from us)
♫ Boe naid bain gwannathar
(All things must pass away)
♫ Boe cuil ban firitha
(All life is doomed to fade)
Silivren penna míriel
(Glittering light falling like shining jewels)
O menel aglar enelath!
(from the firmament the glory of the star-host!
Silivren penna míriel
(Glittering light falling like shining jewels)
...agh burzum-ishi krimpatul
(...and in the darkness bind them)
Ash nazg dur
(One Ring to rule)
♫ Ta han narcho nar Gurth
(Then let death break it)
♫ Gar vethed e-chúnen
(He has the last of my heart)
♫ go hon bedithon na meth
(I will go with him to the end)
♫ han narcho gurth
(Then let death break it)
♫ Gar vethed e-chúnen
(He has the last of my heart)
♫ Na meth
(To the end)
♫ bedithon na meth
(with him to the end)
♫ Nín egor na ngurth nín
(If by my life or death)
♫ Gerin le beriad
(I can protect you)
♫ Le beriathon
(I will)
♫ Le [anon] vegil nín
(I give you my sword)
♫ Cyll e-Gorv
(Ringbearer)
♫ Le annon beth nín
(I give you my word)
♫ Ú-erir aen han risto
(It cannot be broken)
♫ Ú-erir aen han
(Nor turned aside)
♫ Isto Mordor: Elessar!
(Let Mordor know this: Elessar!)
♫ Elessar! Tellin i Gondor!
(Elessar! The Lords of Gondor have come!)
♫ Vi ól
(Lifted up)
♫ Coll e dû
(Borne from the darkness)
♫ Or hiriath naur
(above the rivers of fire)
♫ Na rovail mae
(on wings soft...)
♫ Sui 'waew
(...as the wind)
♫ Man prestant i ardhon?
(What's happened to the world?)
♫ Cerithar aen illiad dim úthe[ne]nin
(Is everything sad going to come untrue?)
♫ Naur
(Fire)
...burzum-ishi krimpatul...
(...in the darkness bind them...)
♫ Sin eriol natha túr in úgarnen
(Only thus its power will be undone)
♫ Mi naurath Orod[dru]in
(Into the fires of Mount Doom)
♫ Boe hedi i Vín
(The One must be cast)
♫ Han i vangad i moe ben bango
(This is the price that must be paid)
♫ Sin eriol natha túr in úgarnen
(Only thus its power will be undone)
♫ Sin eriol ûm beleg úgannen
(Only thus a great evil unmade)
♫ Ú cilith war
(There is no other choice)
♫ Ú men 'war
(There is no other way)
♫ Boe min mebi
(One of you must take it)
♫ Boe min bango
(One of you must pay)
♫ Sin eriol na[tha]
(Only thus)
♫ Úm beleg úgannen
(a great evil unmade)
♫ Ú cilith 'war
(There is no other choice)
♫ Boe min mebi
(One of you must take it)
♫ Boe min bango
(One of you must pay)
♫ Boe hedi i Vín
(The One must be cast)
♫ Sin eriol úm beleg úgannen
(Only thus a great evil unmade)
♫ Go hon bedithon na meth
(I will go with him to the end)
♫ Mi naurath Orodruin...
(Into the fires of Mount Doom...)
♫ ...Boe hedi i Vin
(...The One must be cast)
♫ Bedithon na meth
(With him to the end)
♫ Nu dalav
(Beneath the ground)
♫ Úrui tuiannen na ruith
(Swollen hot with anger)
♫ Leithia Orodruin oe in phan
(Orodruin releases all its ruin)
♫ Orthannen im vi ól
(In a dream I was lifted up)
♫ Coll e dû
(Borne from the darkness)
♫ Na rovail mae sui
(on wings soft as the wind)
♫ Man prestant i ardhon?
(What's happened to the world?)
♫ Cerithar aen dim úthenin?
(Is everything sad going to come untrue?)
Et Eärello
(Out of the Great Sea)
Endorenna utúlien.
(to Middle-earth I am come)
Sinome maruvan
(In this place I will abide)
ar Hildinyar
(and my heirs)
tenn’ Ambar-metta
(unto the ending of the world)
Hannon le.
(Thank you.)
♫ Tinúviel el vanui
(Tinúviel, the elven-fair)
♫ Elleth alfirin edhelhael
(Immortal maiden elven-wise)
I Aear cân ven na mar.
(The sea calls us home.)