♫ Katabrikihu tanakhi uduhu bin-nât aznân tarsisi
(Can breach it, Comes from it, Only an endless darkness rises)
♫ Bazar udu agânî-furkhîn
(Deep from the beginnings of the world)
♫ Ma satf unkhai! Atkât Zatag rafizu
(Nor step too close, The silence will take you)
♫ Irkat-lukhud ma kata[brikihu]
(No shaft of light can breach it)
♫ Ulfat-atam ma...
(No breath of air...)
♫ ...tana[khi] uduhu
(...comes from it)
♫ Bin-nât aznân tarsisi
(Only an endless dark rises)
♫ Bazar udu agânî-furk[hîn]
(Deep from the beginnings of the world)
♫ Gurd!
(Have fear!)
♫ Mettanna
(To the end)
♫ Nárendur
(Servant of fire)
♫ An mauya mahtie
(For you must fight)
♫ Mettana
(To the end)
♫ And on thaere hwile
(And in that moment)
♫ Héo[dréag] thá losinga
(She felt the loss)
♫ Earla thinga the héo forléas
(Of everything that had been missed)
♫ [Ró]mello vanwa, [Va]limar!
(Lost to those of the East is Valimar!)
♫ Namarie! Nai [elye] hiru[va]!
(Farewell! Maybe even thou shalt find it!)
♫ [Ró]mello vanwa, [Va]limar!
(Lost to those of the East is Valimar!)
♫ Nai elyë [hiruva!]
(Maybe even thou shalt find it!)
Hiro hyn hîdh ab ’wanath.
(Let they find peace in the afterlife.)
♫ Ngyrth sí...
(The dead...)
♫ Ngyrth sí ú-los[tar]
(The dead do not sleep here)
♫ Nêbâbîtham Magânanê
(We renounce our Maker)
♫ Nêtabdam dâur
(We cling to the darkness)
♫ Nênâkham
(We are coming)
Aragorn, nad no ennas!
(Aragorn, something’s out there!)
Man cenich?
(What do you see?)
♫ Hwær cwóm helm? Hwær cwóm byrne?
(Where is the helm? Where is the hauberk?)
♫ Hwærcwóm feax flówende?
(Where is the bright hair flowing?)
♫ Hwær cwóm hand on hearpestrenge?
(Where is the hand on the harp string?)
♫ Hwær cwóm scir fýr scinende?
(Where is the red fire glowing?)
♫ Híe hine [sáwon] feorran
(In the distance they saw him)
♫ And hwíte sun[nan in mane]
(White sun caught in his mane)
♫ [Híe lange hine] clipodon
(Long they called him)
♫ Ac hé [ne wolde cuman]
(But he would not come)
♫ For ðon hé wæs Sceadufæx
(For he was Shadowfax)
♫ hláford ealra méara
(Lord of all Horses)
♫ Anhé Neandé
(And he answered only to one)
♫ Mettanna
(To the end)
♫ Lim-strang wæs geboren
(Strong-limbed he was born)
♫ Bearn léod-cyninga
(This son of Kings)
♫ Magorinc Mearces
(This warrior of Rohan)
♫ Bunden in byrde tó lædenne
(Bound by birth to lead)
♫ Bealocwealm hafað fréone frecan forth onsended
(An evil death has set forth the noble warrior)
♫ giedd sculon singan gléomenn sorgiende
(A song shall sing sorrowing minstrels)
♫ on Meduselde þæt he ma no wære,
(in Meduseld that he is no more,)
♫ his dryhtne dyrest and mæga deorost.
(to his lord dearest and kinsmen most belover.)
♫ Bealo...
(An evil death...)
Simbelmynë.
("Evermind")
♫ Of cilde tó menn
(From childhood to a man)
♫ thæt hé his déath geséo
(So that he might face his death)
Westu hál... Ferðu, Théodred, Ferðu.
(Be-thou well... Go-thou, Théodred, go-thou.)
♫ Thæt hearde sóth
(The hard truth)
Fæste.
(Fast.)
Stille nú.
(Be still now.)
Fæste.
(Fast.)
Stille.
(Be still.)
Lac is drefed, gefrægon.
(A battle is stirred up, they heard.)
Hwæt nemnað ðe?
(What is your name?)
Ðin nama is cynglic.
(Your name is kingly.)
Man le trasta, Brego?
(What troubles you, Brego?)
Man cenich?
(What did you see?)
♫ Ú i vethed
(This is not the end)
♫ nâ i onnad
(it is the beginning)
Minlû pedich nin...
(Once you told me...)
i aur hen telitha.
(this day would come.)
Ú i vethed ... nâ i onnad.
(This is not the end... it is the beginning.)
Boe bedich go Frodo.
(You must go with Frodo.)
Han bâd lîn.
(It is your path.)
Dolen i vâd o nin.
(My path is hidden from me.)
Si peliannen i vâd na dail lîn.
(It is already laid before your feet.)
Si boe ú-dhannathach.
(You cannot falter now.)
Arwen...
Ae ú-esteliach nad...
(If you trust nothing else...)
estelio han...
(trust in this...)
estelio ammen.
(trust in us.)
♫ Esteli o han...
(Trust this...)
♫ Estel, le iôn adar lín
(Hope, you are your father’s son)
Nach gwannatha sin?
(Are you going to leave in such way?)
Ma nathach hi gwannathach or minuial archened?
(Did you think you could slip away at first light - unnoticed?)
Ú-ethelithon.
(I will not return.)
Estelio guru lîn ne dagor.
(Trust in your skill in battle.)
Ethelithach.
(You will come back.)
Ú-bedin o gurth ne dagor.
(I don’t speak about death in battle.)
O man pedich?
(What do you speak of?)
Edra le men, men na guil edwen...
(You have a chance for another life...)
haer o auth a nîr a naeth.
(far from war and weeping and woe.)
♫ Hwær cwóm hearpestrenge?
(Where is the harp string?)
♫ Hwær cwóm scir fýr scinende?
(Where is the red fire glowing?)
♫ Hwær cwóm helm?
(Where is the helm?)
♫ Héo dréag thá losinga
(She felt the loss)
♫ Earla thinga the héo forléas
(Of everything that had been missed)
Durbgu Nazg-shu, Durbgu Dash-shu
(Lord of the Ring, Lord of the Earth)
♫ Uich gwennen na 'wanath ah na dhín
(You are not bound to loss and silence)
♫ An uich gwennen na
(For you are not bound)
♫ Boe naid bain gwannathar
(All things must pass away)
♫ Boe cuil ban firitha
(All life is doomed to fade)
Arwen.
Tollen i lû.
(It is time.)
I chair gwannar na Valannor. Si bado, no círar.
(The ships depart to Valinor. Now go, before they sail.)
♫ Úivethed nâ i onnad
(This is not the end, it is the beginning)
♫ Si boe ú-dhanna
(You must not falter now)
♫ Ae ú-esteli, esteliach nad...
(If you trust nothing else...)
♫ Estelio han, estelio han, estelio
(Trust this, trust this, trust)
♫ Estelio han, estelio veleth
(Trust this, trust love)
♫ Estel, le iôn adar lín
(Hope, you are your father’s son)
Ah im, ú-’erin veleth lîn?
Do I not also have your love?
Gerich veleth nîn, ada.
You have my love, father.
♫ Nef Elbereth Gil[thoniel]
(Heavenly Elbereth Kindler of Stars)
♫ Boe naer, [an]nant ui[ch] ben-estel
(Sorrowing, and yet you are not without hope)
♫ Man ammen toltha i dann hen môrn?
(Who brings to us this token of darkness?)
I amar prestar aen,
(The world is changed,)
han mathon ne nen,
(I feel it in the water.)
han mathon ne chae,
(I feel it in the earth,)
♫ Si danna atha nauva
(Now all will fall away)
a han noston ned ’wilith.
(I smell it in the air.)
♫ Mel, melmë nóren sina
(Love, our love for this land)
♫ Nur ala aëaron
(is deeper than the depths of the sea)
♫ Nuruva Tercáno
(The Herald of Death)
♫ I tuo i macil a staldaron Corma
(The strength, the weapon, the needs of the valiant, the Ring...)
Mae carnen, Brego, mellon nîn.
(Well done, Brego, my friend.)
Le abdollen.
(You’re late.)
Hannon le.
(Thank you.)
♫ Echuiannen
(The woods have awoken)
Boe a hyn:
(And they should be...)
Neled herain... dan caer menig.
(Three hundred... against ten thousand.)
Si, beriathar hyn ammaeg na ned Edoras.
(Here they-will-defend themselves sharper than at Edoras.)
Aragorn, nedin dagor hen ú-’erir ortheri.
(Aragorn, they cannot win this fight.)
Natha daged dhaer
(They are all going to die.)
♫ Hwær cwóm helm? Hwær cwóm byrne?
(Where is the helm? Where is the hauberk?)
♫ Hwær cwom feax flowende?
(Where is the bright hair flowing?)
Ú-moe edaved, Legolas
(There is nothing to forgive, Legolas.)
♫ Man ammen toltha i dann hen môrn?
(Who brings to us this token of darkness?)
♫ Si danna atha nauva
(Now all will fall away)
♫ Mel, melmë nóren sina
(Love, our love for this land)
♫ Nur ala aëaron nur
(is deeper than the depths of the sea)
♫ Il[firin] nair[elma]
(Undying is our regret)
Mae govannen, Haldir.
(Well-met, Haldir.)
A Eruchîn, ú-dano i faelas a hyn...
(O Children-of-Eru, don’t show the mercy to them...)
an uben tanatha le faelas!
(for nobody will-show you mercy!)
Dartho!
(Hold!)
Tangado a chadad!
(Prepare to fire!)
Faeg i-varv dîn na lanc...
(Their armour is weak at the neck...)
a nu ranc!
(and beneath the arm!)
Hado i philinn!
(Loose the arrows!)
I philinn! ... Han!
(Arrows! ... forward!)
Pendraid!
(Ladders!)
Na fennas!
(To the causeway!)
Hado ribed! Hado!
(Loose continously! Loose!)
Dago han, Legolas!
(Bring him down, Legolas!)
Dago han!
(Bring him down!)
Hado i philinn!
(Loose the arrows!)
Herio!
(Charge!)
Nan barad!
(To the Tower!)
Haldir!
Nan barad!
(To the Tower!)
♫ Ar sindarn óriello caita mornië
(And out of a grey country darkness lies)
Haldir!
♫ Ar ilye tier unduláve lumbule...
(And all paths are drowned deep in shadow...)
♫ Rithannen i geven
(Earth shakes)
♫ Thangen i harn
(Stone breaks)
♫ Na fennas i daur
(The forest is at your door)
♫ Ôl dûr ristannen
(The dark sleep is broken)
♫ Eryn echuiannen
(The woods have awoken)
♫ I ngelaidh dagrar
(The trees have gone to war)
♫ Ristar thynd, cúa tawar
(Roots rend, wood bends)
♫ Dam[bedir] ganed
(The Ents have answered the call)
♫ Rithannen i geven, Thangen i harn
(Earth shakes, Stone breaks)
♫ Na fennas i daur
(The forest is at your door)
♫ Ôl dûr ristannen
(The dark sleep is broken)
♫ Echuiannen
(The woods have awoken)
♫ i ngelaidh dagra
(The trees have gone to war)
♫ Ristar thynd, cúa tawar
(Roots rend, Wood bends)
Forð Eorlingas!
(Forth Eorlingas!)
♫ [Ir]Kat-lu[hud]
(Shaft of light)
♫ For ðon hé wæs Sceadufæx
(For he was Shadowfax)
♫ hláford ealra méara
(Lord of all Horses)
♫ Anhé Neandé hlá!
(And he answered only to one!)
♫ Rithannen i geven, Thangen i harn
(Earth shakes, Stone breaks)
♫ Na fennas i daur
(The forest is at your door)
♫ Ôl dûr ristannen
(The dark sleep is broken)
♫ Eryn echuiannen
(The woods have awoken)
♫ I ngelaidh dagrar
(The trees have gone to war)
Ristar thynd, Cúa tawar
(Roots rend, Wood bends)